<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>God save the King, or, The loyal and joyfull acclamation of subjects to their King as it was opened in a sermon, preached in one of the congregations of the city of Edinburgh ...</title>
            <author>Lawrie, Robert.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 60 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A49783</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L694</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R34509</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">14471713</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 14471713</idno>
            <idno type="VID">102408</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A49783)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 102408)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1062:24)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>God save the King, or, The loyal and joyfull acclamation of subjects to their King as it was opened in a sermon, preached in one of the congregations of the city of Edinburgh ...</title>
                  <author>Lawrie, Robert.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Christopher Higgins ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed by Wing to Lawrie.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: pages stained.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Thanksgiving Day addresses.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:102408:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:102408:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>God ſave the King: OR, The loyal and joyfull Acclamation of Subjects to their King.</p>
            <p>As it was opened in a SERMON, preached in one of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations of the City of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> upon the day of Solemn Thankſgiving for the King's Majeſty his happy Return and Reſtauration to his Dominions; Kept, <hi>June</hi> 19. 1660. At the Appointment of the Presbyterie of <hi>Edinburgh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>R. L.</hi> One of the Miniſters of the City.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Chron. 29.20.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>And all the Congregation bleſſed the Lord God of their fathers, and bowed down their heads and worſhipped the Lord and the King.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Solennis haec acclamatio, profectò non adulantis eſt, ſed optimum ſuo Regi ſtatum precantis, ac fideli ſervo digna oratio, quando Principes Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoli Chriſtianos homines ad id ſedulò hortantur, ut etiam alienis à Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligione rect<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Magiſtratibus optima quaeque divinitùs precentur.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Job. Wolphius</hi> in <hi>Nehem.</hi> cap. 2. v. 13.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Multi futiliter ita ſalutant Reges ſuos, Sed minimè dubium eſt quin <hi>Daniel</hi> ex animo optaverit Regi longam vitam &amp; faelicem,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Johan. Calvin.</hi> in <hi>Dan.</hi> 6.24.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>EDINB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RGH,</hi> Printed by <hi>Chriſtopher Higgins,</hi> in <hi>Harts</hi> Cloſe, over againſt the Trone-Church, 1660.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:102408:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:102408:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2 King. 11. v. 12.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>—And they clapt their hands, and ſaid, God ſave the King.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here are three expreſſions of a great joy in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.
<list>
                  <item>1. The joy of a woman after her travel, her ſore pangs and bitter ſhowers, <hi>Joh.</hi> 16.21. our Saviour ſaith, That <hi>ſhe remembreth no more her anguiſh, for joy that a man is born into the world.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. The joy of the harveſt, that the husbandman hath, after his labours, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 126.6. <hi>He that goeth forth and weepeth, bearing precious ſeed, ſhall doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe come again with rejoycing, bringing his ſheaves with him.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. The joy of them that divide the ſpoil, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 9.3. <hi>They joy before thee, as men rejoyce when they divide the spoil.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list> All three ariſe from a ſad ground, and this maketh their joy the ſweeter, their bypaſt ſorrows, pangs and labours do feed and encreaſe their preſent joyes, their preſent joyes do compenſe and ſoften their bygone ſorrows.</p>
            <p>The joy of this day, is neither the joy of a woman after travel, nor the joy of the harveſt, nor the joy of them that divide the ſpoil; Yet is it a joy, upon this account rendred moſt ſweet unto us, that it cometh after many ſore pangs, labour and toil, bloud and wounds, and ſad captivity to poor <hi>Scotland.</hi> Had we enjoyed our King in peace, when he was firſt proclaimed and crowned King amongſt us, it would have been matter of great joy to us; But to have him now returned to reign over us, after many a bloudy battel, and long and ſore bondage to us, ten years ſad exile to him, it doth exceedingly heighten our joy: The wiſdom of God's providence, maketh both his and our loſſe and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering an advantage in the end.</p>
            <p>I have read to you, for the ſolemnity of this day, a paſſage that ſetteth forth the expreſſions of the joy of God's people in <hi>Judah,</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the reſtoring of their rightfull Soveraign and lawfull Authority to them. The hiſtory you have in the preceeding part of the Chapter: After that <hi>Abaziah</hi> King of <hi>Judah,</hi> was cruelly murdered by the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of the hoſt, <hi>Jehu, Athaliah</hi> his mother uſurped the Kingdom, ſlew all the Kings ſeed, and reigned tyrannically over <hi>Judah,</hi> the ſpace of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:102408:3"/>ſix years; Yet <hi>Jehoſheba</hi> the Kings ſiſter, the wife of <hi>Jehojada</hi> the High Prieſt, having hid <hi>Joaſh</hi> the Prince, and ſaved him from uſurping <hi>Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liah</hi> her cruelty, <hi>Jehojada</hi> in a convenient time bringeth forth the Kings Son, crowneth him, and inveſteth him in the Government, Upon which, all the people <hi>Clapt their hands, and ſaid, God ſave the King,</hi> in token of their joy and approbation.</p>
            <p>The firſt ſign and expreſſion of their joy, is, Clapping of hands. This, though ſometimes we find it uſed as an expreſſion of grief; yet moſt frequently it is an expreſſion of joy <hi>Pſal.</hi> 47.1. and it is an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of vehement and greateſt joy. The ſecond ſign, is an Accla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, the ordinary ſalutation people gave to their Kings: In the Original, it is, <hi>Let the King live, Vive le Roy,</hi> well tranſlated to us ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the cuſtomary word of our Nation, <hi>God ſave the King.</hi> The life of a King is more precious and of more value, than of many others: 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18.3. the people ſaid to <hi>David, Thou art worth ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand of us.</hi> Many mens lives depend upon his, and the ſafety of thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands upon his ſafety. Therefore this was wont to be a common Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutation uſed towards Princes: good <hi>Nehemiah</hi> ſpoke it to <hi>Artaxerxes, Nehem.</hi> 2.3. and holy <hi>Dantel</hi> (<hi>Dan.</hi> 6.21.) to <hi>Darius</hi> when he came to viſite him in the Lions den, the Prophet ſo ſoon as he heard him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſaid, <hi>O King, live for ever.</hi> And there is more in it than many that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly have it in their mouthes do conſider of: for,
<list>
                  <item>1. Hereby they ſignified their cordial reſpect to the King.</item>
                  <item>2. Their ſerious appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of their own happineſſe, as being bound up in the Kings ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</item>
                  <item>3. Their prayer and heart-wiſhes to God for the Kings life, happineſſe, and welfare.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>I have the rather pitched upon it for the ground of our Doctrine, that whilſt this word is in our mouths at ſuch a ſolemn occaſion, we may be advertiſed how to uſe it religiouſly and to purpoſe, and whilſt this word rings amongſt us, we may minde what is imported thereby.</p>
            <p>The firſt Doctrine then I ſhall preſent you with from the words; <hi>they clapt their hands</hi> for joy is, <hi>That when God is ſo favourable to a people as to eſtabliſh lawfull Authority, their rightfull King over them, it is their du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to rejoyce and be glad.</hi> 1 <hi>Kings,</hi> 1.4 at the inauguration of <hi>Solomon,</hi> they blew the Trumpets and ſaid, God ſave King Solomon: and all the people piped with pipes, and rejoyced with great joy, ſo that the earth rent with the ſound of them. And when <hi>Solomon</hi> was anointed a ſecond time, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>9.22. all the people did eat and drink before the Lord with great gladneſs. The Scripture ſpeaks of ſuch a joy with approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and allowance: becauſe indeed there is good reaſon for it, Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Government ſetled among a people, being both a ſingular bleſſing of God in it ſelf, and the bond of all other bleſſings a people enjoy: it
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:102408:3"/>being like the girdle, that maketh faſt a mans armour and his garments about him; the binding bleſſing that enſures to a people their Peace, their Liberty, their Lives, their Religion, and what elſe they enjoy, as you ſhall hear. In the want of it, all things are looſe, as you may read, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 3.2, 5. Where the Lord threatneth, 1. to take away the <hi>ſtay</hi> and <hi>ſtaff</hi> of their natural life, Then he addeth (as no leſte judgment) that he will break the <hi>ſtay</hi> and <hi>ſtaff</hi> of their civil life, by taking away the Judge, the Prudent, the Ancient: and what followes in the fifth verſe? <hi>The people ſhall be oppreſſed, every one by another,—the childe ſhall behave himſelf proudly againſt the ancient, and the baſe againſt the honourable.</hi> So it is threatned as a ſad judgement, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 3.4. <hi>The children of Iſrael ſhall abide many dayes without a King, and without a Prince:</hi> A ſad condition for a people to be without a King to protect them, to maintain their Lawes, their Liberties, and Priviledges. On the contrary, by the preſence of this bleſſing, all other bleſſings are inſured to a people. See <hi>Pſ.</hi> 72. where the chearfull face of the State, doth ſpeak the comfortable influence of a good King; The people are judged with Righteouſneſs, the poor with Judgment, the mountains bring Peace, the little hills Righteouſneſs.</p>
            <p>I cannot ſtand to reckon all the particular bleſſed fruits of a good Kings Government; But let us conſider at this time theſe five particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Reſtraint of vice by the execution of juſtice, is the fruit of law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Authority ſet up. How often is that inculcat in the Book of <hi>Judges?</hi> Chap. 17.6.18.1.19.1.21.25. <hi>In theſe dayes there was no King in Iſrael, and every man did that which was right in his own eyes.</hi> When there was no King to rule, Idolatrie waxed common without any pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, whoredom and uncleanneſs without controlment, murder and oppreſſion practiſed without any check, a lamentable diſorder and confuſion. It is reported of the <hi>Perſians,</hi> that it was their cuſtom, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the death of their King, to let the people be without all Lawes and Government for ſome dayes, to diſmiſs malefactors, and permit a time of licentious liberty, That ſo they ſeeing the miſchief and inconvenience of being without their King, they might the more willingly ſubmit themſelves to his ſucceſſor. But now when a good King is ſet up, he is a terrour to evill doers, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. And it hath been truly ſaid, if ſome men were not gods among men, moſt men would be beaſts, yea, devils among men in all kind of wickedneſs.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſecond happy fruit of a good Kings Government, is Protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the innocent, the poor and the weak. This goeth along with the former. What is among a people, deſtitute of lawfull Authority, but as <hi>Habakkuk<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> ſpeaketh, Chap. 1.14. <hi>Men are as the fiſhes of the ſea, as the creeping things that have no Ruler over them?</hi> The greater fiſh eat up the leſſer; the rich and wealthie, oppreſſe the poor; the great ones in
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:102408:4"/>whoſe hand is power, bear down the weak and mean ones. But now when the good King is ſet up, the poor have a father and a defender, <hi>the Jawes of the wicked are broken, the ſpoil pluckt from his teeth, Job</hi> 29.16, 17. There is a covering againſt the heat, a hiding place from the wind, a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge from the tempeſt, rivers of waters in a dry land, and the ſhaddow of a rock in a weary land; <hi>In his dayes, the righteous flouriſh: for he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livereth the needy when he cryeth,</hi> the poor and him that hath no helper; He redeemeth their ſoul from deceit and violence, and precious is their bloud in his ſight. Hence are Princes called the Shields of the earth, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 47.9. for the ſafety and defence of the innocent, and the fence they afford to our liberty and propertie; if none will be ſubject, none can be free; if men owne not lawfull Government, they ſhall not call any thing they have their own.</p>
            <p n="3">3. A third happy fruit of a good Kings Government, is peace and quietneſs. <hi>Acts.</hi> 24 2. the Orator <hi>Tertullus,</hi> began his Speech to <hi>Felix</hi> with this, <hi>Seing by thee we enjoy great quietneſs, and that very worthy deeds are done unto this Nation by thy providence; We accept it alwayes—with all thankfulneſs, moſt noble Felix:</hi> Yet <hi>Felix</hi> was none of the beſt Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors: a man far better than <hi>Tertullus,</hi> inſpired by the Spirit of God, the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> exhorteth to pray for Kings and all in Authority, upon this account, that we might live in peace and godlineſs under them. Two wayes is a good King the procurer of Peace, 1. By being a bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wark againſt Invaſions from without, keeping that there be no crying out in our ſtreets, no breaking in, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 144.14. All the dayes of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon, Judah</hi> and <hi>Iſrael</hi> dwelt confidently every man under his own Vine-tree, from <hi>Dan</hi> even to <hi>Beerſheba,</hi> 1 <hi>King.</hi> 4.25.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By being the cement, to unite ſcattered ſocieties within, and the healer of breaches and diſſentions: <hi>Zecha.</hi> 10.4. <hi>Out of Judah came the corner, and the nail.</hi> The good King is not only the corner-ſtone for foundation for a people to reſt on<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and the top-ſtone for ornament, but the corner, that joyns the ſidewalls together; he is not only the nail, for hanging all veſſels great and ſmall upon him, but the nail for joyning the beams and rafters of the houſe and building.</p>
            <p n="4">4. A fourth happy fruit of a good Kings Government, is Plenty. That this followeth upon the former, we cannot but underſtand: for, when all things run in a right channell the lawes of the land are in force under lawfull Authority, people enjoying their liberties, lives, poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and houſes in peace; Then Induſtrie, Learning, Arts, Trade, Traffick, are encouraged and advanced, and a people proſper even in externall things. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 9.27. You read that <hi>Solomon</hi> brought in ſuch wealth into <hi>Judea</hi> by his good Government, his advancing Trade and Traffick by ſea and land, that ſilver was nothing accounted of through the abundance of it: Yea, God Almighty alſo from above, ſeconds the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:102408:4"/>bleſſing of righteous Government with the dew of heaven and the ſat of the earth, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 72.16. <hi>There ſhall be a handfull of corn upon the top of the mountains, the fruit thereof ſhall ſhake like Lebanon;</hi> a litle ſhall yeeld a plentifull increaſe: and left it ſhould be ſaid, this is for the villages and country, it is added, <hi>They of the City ſhall flouriſh like graſſe of the earth;</hi> they ſhall be green and grow in proſperity and wealth.</p>
            <p n="5">5. A fifth happy fruit of a good Kings Government, and which is the chief of all, is the comfortable uſe of the Goſpel, and the liberty of the Ordinances of Jeſus Chriſt, holy freedom of conſcience, which is the very marrow of our bones, and life of our lives, when now the Church hath a nurſing father, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49.23. and the good King be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes, under God, a defence upon all the glory, according to the title of our Kings, <hi>A Defender of the Faith of the Goſpel.</hi> Many Heathen people have enjoyed happy dayes, for Protection, Plenty and Proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity under their heathen Kings, as the Romans under their <hi>Auguſtus, Trajan, Adrian, Titus:</hi> But when the King is a member of the Church, and is one of Chriſt's Kings, who holds his Crown in ſubordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the King of Saints, Then, beſide all outward bleſſings to the State, there is a far greater enjoyed; The Goſpel hath free paſſage, the Ordinances of Chriſt are maintained in purity, Error and Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, Idolatry, falſe Worſhip, Atheiſm and Irreligion are baniſhed: for, the Chriſtian King is as <hi>Conſtantine</hi> to the Church, <hi>Epiſcopus extra Eccleſiam,</hi> a watchman and overſeer to her. We all read what good offices <hi>David, Hezekiah,</hi> and <hi>Joſiah</hi> did unto the Church, advancing true Religion and right Worſhip, defacing Idolatry; and of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy <hi>Joſhua,</hi> who lived before them, it is ſaid, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 24.31. <hi>That all the dayes of</hi> Joſhua <hi>the people ſerved the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now in all theſe reſpects it is, that a good King is compared to the Light, whoſe riſing makes a day unto a people, whoſe ſetting and obſcuring makes their night, as the Ancients expound that 24. verſe of the 118 <hi>Pſalm,</hi> that was ſung at the inauguration of <hi>David, This is the day which the Lord hath made, we will be glad and rejoyce in it:</hi> It is called a <hi>day,</hi> becauſe of the Occurrents of the time, that <hi>David</hi> had riſen upon them like a Sun to make a lightſom day. The 104. <hi>Pſalm</hi> tels you what difference there is betwixt the day and the night; The night is the time when the ſavage beaſts range abroad, Wolves, Lions and Serpents creep out from their dens and holes: But when the day appears, theſe beaſts retire to their caves, and man goeth forth to his labour. So it is in times of confuſion, when Government is caſt looſe, all ſorts of beaſtly men; filthy as Swine, greedy as Wolves, cruel as Tygers, deceitfull as Crocodiles, they come abroad boldly to ſatisfie their luſts: But in time of lawfull Authority, when a King is on the Throne, theſe vermine are chaſed to their holes and dens, as
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:102408:5"/>is declared at large, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 101. and honeſt men come forth, appear and lift up their heads.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Application.</hi> Thus you have ſeen the Doctrine, Let us apply it to our Caſe. We are aſſembled this day to bleſſe God for reſtoring our Kings Majeſty to his Dominions: Now, if any people ever had cauſe to rejoyce upon ſuch an occaſion, we much more, Conſidering the unparallel'd circumſtances of this our great mercy. I deſire you to conſider of them in theſe five.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>What</hi> is the bleſſing reſtored to us.</item>
               <item>2. <hi>When,</hi> the circumſtance of time.</item>
               <item>3. <hi>How,</hi> the manner.</item>
               <item>4. <hi>Who:</hi> for a King is ſet over us.</item>
               <item>5. To <hi>Whom</hi> all this goodneſſe is manifeſted, a very undeſerving people.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>What.</hi> 1. What is the bleſſing reſtored to us? Even our ancient fundamental Government, under which theſe Kingdoms have enjoyed both the Goſpel and Peace, under which our progenitors have enjoyed many happy and good dayes by the Royal protection of our Kings. It hath unhappily come in debate in theſe late times of confuſion, what kind of Government is the beſt? But whoever might have diſputed ſuch a caſe, it did no wayes become theſe Nations to do it, Kingly Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment being of ſo old and firm and undubitable poſſeſſion amongſt us. In this Nation ſome hundred years before Chriſts incarnation it was eſtabliſhed: And if we go to the Scripture with it, ſure I am, there is none will vye with it, the very hiſtory of the lives of the Kings of the people of God, taking up a great part of the Bible; and Kingly Government being ſuch a fair Image of God Almighties Government in the world, and Chriſts Kingdom in the Church, that the whole diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſations of providence, the whole diſpenſations of grace in the Goſpel, are ſet forth to us under the expreſſions of <hi>King</hi> and <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom:</hi> Every other word of the Goſpel ſoundeth forth a King and Kingdom to us; And why doth the New Teſtament in many places, where duty to the Magiſtrate is preſſed, expreſly and particularly men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>Kings,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13. and v. 17. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.2. if not to ſet the ſeal and approbation of the holy Ghoſt upon Kingly Government in ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial?</p>
            <p>And though it be ſaid in Scripture of <hi>Saul,</hi> that God gave <hi>Iſrael</hi> a King in His wrath, and took him away in His diſpleaſure; Yet this can no manner of wayes rub upon Kingly Government, ſeing it is moſt clear from theſe two, that Kingly Government was not given them in wrath, but in much mercy,
<list>
                  <item>1. That in <hi>Moſes</hi> time the Lord had ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, that they ſhould be ruled by Kings, <hi>Deut.</hi> 17. and <hi>Moſes</hi> himſelf was King in <hi>Jeſurum.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. That after <hi>Saul,</hi> God gave them a <hi>David</hi> in great love: and we may eaſily perceive that the times of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> and <hi>Solomon,</hi> were the beſt times that ever <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſaw, for Religion,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:102408:5"/>Peace and Proſperity; they were never ſo godly, never ſo wealthy and well every way, as under them.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>I remember, when that prevailing Faction in <hi>England,</hi> made their Act, rejecting Kingly Government, they put in this as a reaſon, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it had been burdenſome and troubleſome to the Nations; But I appeal to all who have conſidered, whether their little finger, hath not been more burdenſom, than the loyns of an hundred of our Kings: And I cannot forget what an Engliſh Divine hath truly printed of their Commonwealth, <hi>That we had</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>never ſo much common poverty, as ſince we became a Commonwealth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>When.</hi> The ſecond circumſtance, is the time <hi>When</hi> God hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored this bleſſing to us, After a dark night of Confuſion, a ſad Interruption that hath been for many years. I told you what the <hi>Perſians</hi> did in policy, to make the people eſteem more highly of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment being eſtabliſhed; But God in his wiſdom hath ſo diſpoſed of us, that we have ſeen not only a few dayes confuſion, but have been under ſad diſtractions for many years, that we might learn more highly to prize the bleſſing of lawfull Government when reſtored.</p>
            <p>In King <hi>James</hi> the ſixth his time, we had a very clear and fair day, a day like <hi>Joſhua's</hi> day, that continued for a long time. In King <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt his time, we had a fair day, for the bleſſings of Government continued with us, till the ſins of all ranks coming to a great height, our day was turned into a very black night; and now in reſpect of the comfortable bleſſings of Kingly Government, we have had a ſad interruption for many years. Yea, and when after the deteſtable and execrable Murder committed upon Him, We in this Nation expected a dawning of our day, by calling home our preſent Kings Majeſty to <hi>Scotland,</hi> and crowning him here; Behold it fell out to us as it is, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 21.12. <hi>The morning cometh, and the night alſo.</hi> Our <hi>morning</hi> was ſoon turned into a <hi>night</hi> of captivity for ten years: And as it is with the natural night, that it is darkeſt juſt before day; So before this appearing of light, there was the greateſt darkneſſe of confuſion and reeling, The righteous Lord overturning, overturning one thing after another, till he ſhould come whoſe right it was. And now that the Lord hath made light to ariſe, after ſo long, ſo black and diſmal confuſions, How ſhould it make us rejoyce? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 118.27. <hi>God is the Lord, who hath ſhewed us light: binde the ſacrifice with cords, even unto the horus of the Altar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>How.</hi> A third Circumſtance is <hi>How.</hi> There is a book in Scripture that hath its name <hi>ECHAH,</hi> the book of <hi>Hows,</hi> and there are many dolefull <hi>Hows</hi> in it, the book of the <hi>Lamentations; How doth the City ſit ſolitary? How is the Gold become dim?</hi> But in this our mercy, there are ſo many joyfull <hi>Hows,</hi> that I cannot reckon all to you: look upon theſe
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:102408:6"/>four,
<list>
                  <item>1. How unexpectedly?</item>
                  <item>2. How ſuddenly?</item>
                  <item>3. How ſweetly?</item>
                  <item>4. How wonderfully?</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. How unexpectedly? Were not all doors of hope ſhut upon us? Eſpecially two things ſeemed to have barred the door upon this bleſſing,
<list>
                  <item>1. The great alienation of heart, found in many of the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, from the King and his Family: It was ſaid of David, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 118.22. <hi>The ſtone which the builders refuſed, is become the head</hi> ſtone <hi>of the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</hi> The Maſter-builders had rejected him, yet was he advanced; they who had formerly rejected him, coming to him (2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 5.1.) and ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>we are thy bone and thy fleſh,</hi> So God hath wrought for our Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne.</item>
                  <item>2. Another impediment that ſtood betwixt us and all hope of this bleſſing, was, that the power and ſtrength of all Armies within theſe Lands, ſtood againſt the King; all Armies were on the contrair part: There was an <hi>Abner</hi> for <hi>Saul,</hi> but not a <hi>Joab</hi> theſe many years to appear for <hi>David.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list> Now this makes the change miraculous, that the very Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies that ſtood againſt, are now turned for him; And that a more noble and generous perſon than <hi>Abner,</hi> did ſend unto our King, and with bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſucceſſe then he (2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 3.12.) ſaying, <hi>Whoſe is the Land? my hand ſhall be with thee to bring about all Iſrael to thee.</hi> God, who doth in the Armies of the heaven and earth, what pleaſeth him, <hi>Dan.</hi> 4.35. He hath turned all the power of Armies by ſea and land for him.</p>
            <p n="2">2. How ſuddenly was this done? <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66.8. <hi>Who hath heard ſuch a thing? who hath ſeen ſuch things? ſhall the earth be made to bring forth in one day? or ſhall a Nation be born at once,</hi> in ſo ſhort a ſpace, that the Lord hath created a new face of affairs, and made the hearts of three Nations to bow to their King at one time? This is the Lords doing, and may be marvellous in our eyes.</p>
            <p n="3">3. How ſweetly is this done? <hi>ſine ſudore, ſine ſanguine,</hi> without ſweat or toyl, without bloud-ſhed; No man loſt his goods, no man loſt his life in this late revolution; Every one were, not long ſince, prog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſticating ſad things, if ever we got a ſetled Government again; we can look for it no otherwiſe than through a ſea of bloud. But, Behold! God hath diſappointed all theſe fears, and the hopes alſo of the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of our peace, who fret and rage, and gnaſh their teeth, ſeeing their expectation fruſtrated.</p>
            <p n="4">4. How wonderfully? <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.32. we may apply that paſſage, <hi>Ask now of the dayes that are paſt, which were before thee, ſince the day that God created man upon earth, and ask from the one ſide of heaven to the other, whether there hath been any ſuch thing, as this great thing is, or hath been heard like it?</hi> No hiſtory hath the parallel of it, a King thruſt away with the hight of contempt, the ſame King returned in the higheſt glory, honour, reſpect and obſervance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Who.</hi> A Fourth Circumſtance in this mercie, and a main one, is
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:102408:6"/>
               <hi>Who,</hi> For a King is reſtored to us. It is true that I read in <hi>Euſebius</hi> his <hi>Eccleſ. Hiſt.</hi> That it was laid to a Miniſters charge as a challenge, <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus eſt Imperatorem in ore beatum dicere:</hi> a ſmall praiſe before a Kings face. may be interpreted adulation; but a great praiſe behind his back, may be no more than a juſt debt. This one thing I am ſure of, from the Word of God, That next to the honour of Chriſt, his Goſpel and his Grace, nothing is more a Miniſters duty, than to advance the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and due eſteem of lawfull Authority in peoples hearts; For, next to <hi>Fear God,</hi> is <hi>Honour the King.</hi> And the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> preſſeth upon <hi>Titus</hi> and all Miniſters, as a ſpeciall part of their work, <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.1. <hi>Put people in minde to be Subject unto Principalities and Powers.</hi> He himſelf preſſeth it to purpoſe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1. <hi>Let every ſoul be Subject, &amp;c.</hi> The Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> runs in the ſame ſtraine, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13. And truly a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter cannot do a worſe turn in his ſtation, than to diminiſh the due cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit of the lawfull Magiſtrate by any ſpeech in publick before the people. The Apoſtle <hi>Jude<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> v. 8. ſtands not to call them <hi>filthy dreamers, who deſpiſe dominion, and ſpeak evil of dignities.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now, what I have to ſay of the Kings Perſon, ſhall be ſummed up in theſe ſix.</p>
            <p n="1">1. We have cauſe to rejoyce, that the righteous Heir of the Kingdom is reſtored to his Throne. This is the great joynt that God hath put in for the healing of thoſe broken Nations: uſually you ſee in Pieces of work that are joyned by Mortiſes and Tenons, when the principal tenon is made faſt, all the reſt of the parts clap together eaſily. <hi>David</hi> experienced it to be ſo, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 75.3. <hi>The earth and all the inhabitants there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of are diſſolved, but I uphold the pillars of it:</hi> all was out of joynt, till he who had Gods right and mans to Govern, came to the Throne, then proved he a healer to their broken and disjoynted parts.</p>
            <p n="2">2. There is cauſe of joy in this, that he is a King of ſo good expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <hi>Hiram,</hi> King of <hi>Tyrus,</hi> was a prudent man, and a godly proſolyte, and when he ſaw <hi>Solomon's</hi> Letters, wherein he diſcovered his pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and affection to the houſe of God, though <hi>Solomon</hi> had not as yet given many other proofs of his wife Government; he congratulats the happineſs of the land, ſaying, <hi>becauſe God loved Iſrael, therefore hath be made</hi> Solomon <hi>King,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 2.11. And what may we ſay of the Gracious Letters and Meſſages, our King did ſend, before himſelf came, to his people? They found themſelves bound at <hi>London</hi> to keep a So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Thankſgiving, even for theſe Gracious Letters and Meſſages.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Let me adde, a King of ſo generall approbation, that hath the good teſtimony of all that know him, for Prudence, Clemency, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, Sobriety, and Piety. Great is his renown among the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed abroad for his conſtancie in the Proteſtant Faith, in the midſt of many aſſaults and tentations</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:102408:7"/>
            <p n="4">4. A King tryed by many afflictions: he cometh out of the furnace of tryall. It was all the better for <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that <hi>David</hi> came by the croſs to the Crown: all the better for <hi>England,</hi> that Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> came out of a Priſon to reign. Though we ought to be grieved for his long and ſad afflictions; Yet, may we not hope, that it ſhall come to paſſe as <hi>Joſeph</hi> ſpoke to his brethren, <hi>Gen.</hi> 50.20? You intended it for evil, but God hath turned it into good, for the ſaving of much people alive. Though men intended his down-bearing for evill, Yet we may hope God will turn it into good unto theſe Nations, that he may be fitter to Govern theſe Nations, being ſo long in the ſchool of hard affliction.</p>
            <p n="5">5. A King glorious by many deliverances, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18.50. <hi>Great delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances giveth he to his King, and ſheweth mercy to his anointed, even to</hi> Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid. As many Countries as he hath been in, with as many great deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verances hath God compaſſed him, from dangers both ſpirituall and bodily, <hi>Scotland, England, France, Holland, Flanders, Germany</hi> and <hi>Spain.</hi> I believe if we get the hiſtory of his Travels publiſhed, the world will ſee how in all thoſe places he hath been miraculouſly preſerved from many dangers.</p>
            <p n="6">6. A King ſignally owned of God now in reſtoring him after all his troubles to his Dominions. His enemies were wont to talk of ſignall Providences, when they carried a day in battell againſt him, and did boaſt of theſe as if God had approved of their doings; But ſee, if among all they can reckon, they can ſpeak of ſuch a ſignall providence as this. It is obſerved of the Egyptian Magicians their blindneſſe, that they could not ſee the finger of God, till the plague of lice came, and then in the leaſt, they were found Confeſſing, this is the finger of God; whereas if their eyes had been opened, they might have ſeen <hi>ambas ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> his whole ten fingers, in their ten plagues; So may it be ſaid to theſe who are not convinced of a work of God in this, they may ſee not only the finger of God, but both his hands, even his ten fingers, not in ten plagues, but ten gracious diſcoveries of his holy attributes. See,
<list>
                  <item>1. the print of his Power, that mighty finger of God, clearly appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Zech.</hi> 4 6. <hi>Not by might, nor by power, but by my Spirit, ſaith the Lord.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. The print of his Mercy, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18.50. <hi>He ſheweth mercy to his anointed,</hi> and to us alſo a ſinfull people.</item>
                  <item>3. Of his juſtice, the Lord ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing againſt Oppreſſours, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 51.13. <hi>Where is the fury of the Oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſour?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. Of his Truth and Faithfulneſs, making good his word. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 125.3. <hi>The rod of the wicked ſhall not reſt alwayes upon the lot of the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>5. His Wiſdom, in bringing order out of confuſion, and light out out of darkneſſe.</item>
                  <item>6. His Zeal in vindicating his Providence from the Blaſphemies caſt upon it.</item>
                  <item>7. His daunting Majeſty, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing in the quieting of all hearts, upon the diſcovery of this work; <hi>Be ſtill, and know, that I am the Lord, I will be exalted in the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:102408:7"/>earth:</hi> it is the language of this diſpenſation, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 46.10.</item>
                  <item>8. His Providence both for our King and us, when we were ſo very low, that we knew not what next to do, he hath remembred us in our low eſtate, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 136.23.</item>
                  <item>9. Pitie and Forebearance, in the tender way of bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it about, not ſurcharging theſe poor harraſſed Nations with new wars and troubles.</item>
                  <item>10. His Holineſſe: <hi>David</hi> ſaid, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 60.6. <hi>God hath ſpoken in his holineſſe, I will divide Schechem, and mete out the valley of Succoth:</hi> his Holineſſe was engaged to give him victory over his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies that were profane, and peaceable poſſeſſion of his own People; and his Holineſſe doth certainly ſhine forth in bearing down all rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious oppoſition to Princes, and oppoſing himſelf to a profane and lawleſſe crew.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>To whom.</hi> the fifth Circumſtance, is the people <hi>to whom</hi> this good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is manifeſted: and this is not the leaſt in illuſtrating the glory of the deliverance, that God ſhould have beſtowed theſe mercies on us, a ſinfull and unworthy people, to whom he may well ſay, as it is, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.32. <hi>Not for your ſakes do I this, be it known unto you: Be aſhamed and confounded for your own wayes, O houſe of Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, for concluſion of this point, I ſay this, We are allowed to rejoyce in this great mercy, in this ſingular bleſſing: But let us take heed how we rejoyce, 1. That there be no exceſſe in the expreſſions of our rejoycing: It is not unlawfull to expreſſe our joy by Meats, Drinks, Triumphs and other Solemnities, <hi>Nehem.</hi> 8<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Yet let us not run into exceſſe. We have done well this day to begin our expreſſions of joy in coming to the Church to hear Gods Word, and to preſent our ſpiritual ſacrifices of prayers and praiſes unto God. Let us take a holy ſtamp of fear and love to God upon our hearts to the door with us, that may be a reſtraint from exceſſe. Remember the Kings Majeſty his Proclamation againſt prophane and debaucht Drinkings; and how pungent that word is, <hi>We are ſufficiently aſhamed of ſuch, who give no other evidence of their affection to Us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Let not our joy be a mere carnal joy, that hath no higher riſe than an earthly contentment; that hath no other operation than what is ſenſual and earthly; that looketh no higher than the creature, and hath <hi>ſelf</hi> for its utmoſt end: But let us rejoyce with a ſpiritual joy, that God may have the chief ſhare in all our triumphs. joyes and exultations; That God may be the principal object of our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycings, and our joy may riſe up to holy admirings and exaltations, and extolling of him, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.3. <hi>O magnifie the Lord with me, and let us exalt his Name together.</hi> If we exclude God out of the play this day, all our joy ſhall be but as crackling of thorns under a pot; Yea, we ſhall not be far from the ſin of thoſe Angels that fell, and of <hi>Adam,</hi> who were contented to rejoyce in their priviledges, but not in
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:102408:8"/>God who gave them, And ſo provoked God to rob them of them <hi>David</hi> is a good example of rejoycing in mercies, who in all his <hi>Pſalms</hi> doth more remember by whom he was made happy, than how hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie he was, eſteeming more highly of the giver, than of any gift.</p>
            <p>The ſecond expreſſion of this peoples joy, is in a loud acclamation, <hi>God ſave the King;</hi> In the Original it is, <hi>Let the King live.</hi> Which, as you heard, was the uſual Salutation to the Kings of old. And the words do expreſſe three things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, The peoples cordial affection to the King, which is the duty of all loyal Subjects to their King, highly to tender and regard, even from their hearts, the Kings happineſſe and welfare. See how the Scripture preſſeth all cordial reſpects to Kings, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 10.20. <hi>Curſe not the King, no not in thy thought. Exod.</hi> 22.28. <hi>Thou ſhalt not revile the gods, nor curſe the Ruler of thy people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>One of the Ancients, writing upon 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6. where God ſmote the men of <hi>Bethſhemeſh</hi> for looking irreverently into the Ark, hath this Note, that God ſmote them, <hi>non ſolum quia inſpexerunt, ſed quia de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpexerunt;</hi> becauſe the Ark had been taken captive, and in the Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtins hands for ſome time they lookt upon it with contempt. The Ark was a ſign of Gods Authority, and God was ſo diſpleaſed when his Authority was contemned, that he ſmot fifty thouſand for it. Although our King hath been brought very low, hath been under ſad captivity and exile, Let none, when he is now returned, deſpiſe him, or look with leſſe reverence upon him: The lower he hath been brought by his afflictions, we ſhould ſet him the higher in our affections. And will you conſider how the Apoſtle <hi>Peter,</hi> twice in one Chapter, preſſeth Submiſſion and Honour to Kings; and yet the Kings who ruled at that time, were heathen and ſtrangers to the Church. And if this precept ſtandeth in force towards a heathen King and ſtranger, What then is to be done of us to ſuch a King as God hath given us, a King of our own Nation, lineally deſcended of the ancient Kings of this Realm, and a Chriſtian King that ſtandeth for the Goſpel and Proteſtant Faith?</p>
            <p>Three things eſpecially ſhould make us yeeld all cordial reſpect to our King. 1. Regard to God, whoſe Image he beareth, being Gods Deputy and Vice-gerent, whom God hath ſtamped with his own Authority; God hath put his own Name upon Kings, <hi>I have ſaid, ye are Gods, Pſal.</hi> 82.6. As to minde them of their duty, that they ſhould rule as God doth, and for God, with a mind like God, free from the mixture of a private ſpirit; So to minde people of their duty, freely to ſubmit, come under and reverence them, as viſible gods, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring any diſhonour done to them, reflecteth upon God whoſe Name they bear.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:102408:8"/>
            <p n="2">2. Reſpect to the Kings Government over us, ſhould make us yeeld all cordial affection to him. The honour of Rulers, is as uſefull to them, as credit is to Merchants: take away credit from the Merchant, he can neither buy nor ſell, trade nor traffick; So a King can neither reward, nor puniſh, nor do any part of his duty as a King, if you take away his credit and honour from him: If a King be robbed of his honour, he hath little behind to loſe, and while he keepeth that unblemiſht, he cannot be at a great loſſe for any thing elſe.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Reſpect to our own benefit ſhould move us to this: if a man caſt down the light of the Kings countenance, let him take heed how he puts down his own; If a Nation will not acknowledge their own head, they muſt unavoidably be made the tail of all other Nations; they that will not ſubmit to lawfull Government, they are made to ſubmit to confuſion and deſtruction: If the light of <hi>Iſrael</hi> be quenched, <hi>Iſrael</hi> muſt be in darkneſſe; and doubtleſſe the light of a Nation is quenched, when a King groweth cheap in vulgar opinion, and a Prince falleth under the undervaluings of his own people.</p>
            <p>Wo to them then that entertain the leaſt diſloyal, irreverent and ſeditious thought againſt the King. Search the Scripture, and you will find the Seditious and Rebellious for the moſt part met with, even in this life. Of ſuch perſons, <hi>Jezabel,</hi> though a naughty woman, ſpake truly, <hi>Had</hi> Zimri <hi>peace who ſlew his Maſter? Jehu, Jeroboam, Zimri, Shallum, Pekah,</hi> the ſervants of <hi>Joaſh,</hi> or <hi>Amnon,</hi> they found it all moſt true. Two eſpecial Beacons are ſet up in Scripture,
<list>
                  <item>1. The puniſhment of <hi>Korah</hi> and his complices, whom the earth opening, ſwallowed up. It is terrible to ſee the ſea ſwallow down a ſhip full of people, crying out for fear; It was far more terrible to ſee the ſolid earth rend and ſwallow thoſe down: it made all <hi>Iſrael</hi> cry and fly aback.</item>
                  <item>2. Another is the fall of <hi>Abſolom,</hi> who roſe againſt <hi>David:</hi> his hair is made his halter, and whilſt he hangs in the Oak, <hi>Joab</hi> and his followers pierce him through with darts every one tryes his weapon on ſo fair a mark; one death is not ſufficient for <hi>Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lom,</hi> he is at once hanged, pierced, mangled, and ſtoned: juſtly is he lift up on the tree, who lift up himſelf againſt his Father and Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign; juſtly is he pierced through, that pierced the Kings heart with many ſorrows; juſtly is he mangled, who had divided and diſmem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred all <hi>Iſrael:</hi> He was caſt forth in a ditch, and a heap of ſtones raiſed above him, which remaineth to this day, and travellors as they paſſe by, caſt to their ſtone, and ſay with a ſolemn execration, <hi>Curſed be the Paricide Abſolom,</hi> and curſed be all Traitours.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Theſe words do expreſſe their deep apprehenſion of their own happineſſe, being bound up in the Kings wel-fare. <hi>Calvine</hi> on the 72. <hi>Pſal.</hi> giving the argument of the <hi>Pſalm</hi> and the ſcope of it, hath
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:102408:9"/>theſe words, <hi>docet veram piorum faelicitatem in eo poſitam eſſe, dum ſub ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nu Regis divinitus. Electi reguntur;</hi> that the whole tract of the <hi>Pſalm</hi> holdeth forth, that it is a great felicity to Gods people on earth, to be governed by a righteous King of Gods chooſing, who is the man of Gods right hand. And <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeaks out the matter clearly, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 10.17. <hi>Bleſſed art thou, O Land, when thy King is the ſon of Nobles, and thy Princes eat in due ſeaſon, for ſtrength and not for drunkenneſs.</hi> The Original hath it, <hi>Thy Bleſſedneſſes, O Land,</hi> as wondering at the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude and greatneſſe of them. And the qualities expreſſed there, are Nobility of birth and education and Sobriety or Temperance: the firſt, becauſe as <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> hath it in his Politicks, <hi>they that are taken from vile degree unto principality, do oftentimes hurt the Government:</hi> for, nothing is more ſharp and bitter, than a baſe perſon exalted; <hi>Aſperius nihil eſt hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mili, &amp;c.</hi> The Spirit of God therefore wiſely provided, (as one obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth) who being to make <hi>Moſes</hi> a Ruler, would not have a fiſher-man draw him out of the waters, but <hi>Pharaohs</hi> daughter, that he might be enobled by his education; And where a noble birth is beautified with a noble Education in vertue, The King is the ſon of Nobles indeed, of white ones, as the Original hath it. The other quality is Temperance, a very ſingular ornament in Kings: Therefore <hi>Cicero</hi> in his C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ation for King <hi>Deiotarus,</hi> ſaith, <hi>Did ever any ſee</hi> Deiotarus <hi>drunk?</hi> Now both theſe being eminent in our King, Why may we not apply the Scripture, <hi>O thy Bleſſedneſſes, O Land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is remarkable, that in all languages, the word that expreſſeth a King, doth hold forth the neceſſity and uſefullneſſe of that Government. The Hebrew word <hi>MELECH,</hi> cometh from a root that ſignifyeth, <hi>counſel:</hi> and the Scripture calleth him the Head of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, as for Supremacy, ſo for Counſels, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.17. Again the Greek word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſignifieth he is the <hi>baſis,</hi> the <hi>foundation</hi> whereon a people ſtand, reſt, and are edifyed: Thus he is not only the Head, but the feet too: Hence that word of <hi>Luther, Unus tantum ſubditus in civitate Magiſtratus,</hi> There is but one ſubject in the Citie the Magiſtrate: the weight of all lyeth upon him, he beareth a people and their burdens, <hi>I am not able to bear this people alone</hi> ſaid <hi>Moſes.</hi> The Latine word <hi>Rex,</hi> is a <hi>regendo,</hi> to govern. Thus he is the hand to the Body politick, that governs the body: The Scripture calleth him the Arm of a people, <hi>Jer.</hi> 48.25. <hi>The horn of</hi> Moab <hi>is cut off, and his arm is broken.</hi> In our language, the word <hi>King,</hi> cometh from the old Teu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonick <hi>Coming,</hi> that ſignifies <hi>knowledge:</hi> thus he is the eye of a people al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, and ſo called in Scripture, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 29.10. <hi>God hath cloſed your eyes:</hi> and, How? In the next words it is expounded, <hi>Your Prophet and your Rulers hath he covered:</hi> and will you add the word of <hi>Lam.</hi> 4.20. <hi>The breath of our Noſtrils:</hi> which ſpeaketh no leſs than this, that it is as poſſible
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:102408:9"/>for a man to live without breath, as for a people to ſubſiſt without Magiſtracy. And who doth not ſee, how many wayes a good King is neceſſary and uſefull to a people? When Kings and Rulers are taken away, the eye of the Common-wealth is put out, and we are left in blindneſs; the foundation is pulled away, and how can the houſe but fall? The feet are cut off, and how can the body ſtand? The head is gone, and there is no counſell; The arm is broken, and there is no ſtrong rod to be a Scepter to rule, and this is for a lamentation and ſhall be for a lamentation, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 19.14. The breath of a Peoples Noſtrils is ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, and what then followes but death to the whole body? Good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon therefore have a people to apprehend this, and be ſenſible of it, That their happineſs is bound up in the happineſs and welfare of their King, and in the ſenſe thereof to cry out, with loud acclamations, <hi>Let the King live;</hi> Let him live, that we may all live, that the Land may live, that Religion may live, Counſell may live, Juſtice may live, Peace may live, that we and our poſterity may have a Reſt, a Center of quietneſs under his ſhadow.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, This acclamation hath in it a ſhort prayer, and an hearty wiſh to God for the Kings ſafety and welfare. Our tranſlation, and the word we uſe, <hi>God ſave the King,</hi> expreſſeth this moſt fully: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Leſſon is clear. That as it is our duty to praiſe God for our King, So to pray to God earneſtly for him. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.12. The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> exhorteth to this <hi>I exhort therefore that firſt of all, ſupplications, prayers. interceſſions and giving of thanks be made for all men, for Kings and all that are in Authority, that we may lead a godly and peaceable life under them.</hi> The Apoſtle ſaith <hi>firſt of all,</hi> becauſe this is a matter of prime conſideration and remembrance, that ſhould have a principall place in all Church-aſſemblies; as to ſeek God for a bleſſing on all holy and ſpirituall, ſo alſo upon all civill adminiſtrations, and the perſons by whom they are adminiſtred. He mentioneth <hi>Kings</hi> in particular, for two reaſons, at Interpreters agree, 1. Becauſe at that time, Kings were ſtrangers to the Goſpel, unconverted and heathen; and people might doubt, whether being ſo, they ſhould pray for them. The Apoſtle looſeth the doubt. <hi>I exhort you pray for them,</hi> notwithſtanding, for your peace ſake: Yea, <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſebius</hi> telleth us, that not only <hi>Conſtantine</hi> and <hi>Juſtinian</hi> ſought the prayers of the Chriſtian Church for them, but that even heathen Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours, (ſome of them) though otherwiſe evil affected to Chriſtianity, Yet had ſuch an eſteem of Chriſtians prayers, that they thought them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and their Empire more ſecure by them, as appears by the Edict of <hi>Galerius Maximinus, Euſebius, Lib.</hi> 8. <hi>Cap.</hi> 29. <hi>Unde Chriſtiani hac indulgentiâ à nobis conceſſa devincti, debent Deo ſuo obnixè ſupplicare pro noſtrâ, Reipublicae, pro ſua ipſorum ſalute, &amp;c.</hi> And it was charged upon <hi>Gallus,</hi> who ſucceeded <hi>Decius,</hi> though he was a heathen, that beginning by cruel Edicts to proſcribe Religious Chriſtians, who were
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:102408:10"/>wont to make earneſt prayers for him, in driving them away, it is ſaid he drave away with them, theſe prayers alſo which were accuſtomed to be poured out to God for him.</p>
            <p n="2">2. For this reaſon alſo doth the Apoſtle particularly mention Kings, to intimate what bleſſed Inſtruments they might be to the Church of God, being converted to the faith of the Goſpel; being members of the Church themſelves, they bring in their glory and honour to the Church, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.24. And this was Gods promiſe to his Church, long before <hi>John's</hi> time, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60.16. <hi>Thou ſhalt ſuck the milk of the Gentiles, and thou ſhalt ſuck the breſt of Kings.</hi> And Oh! how glorious things are ſpoken of the Church there, when it is ſo, <hi>for copper, I will bring gold; for iron, ſilver, &amp;c.</hi> to the end of the Chapter.</p>
            <p>Let me add three motives more to this point, 1. Kings, above all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, ſhould be prayed for: becauſe the Lord challengeth a ſpeciall work upon the hearts of Kings, <hi>Prov.</hi> 21.1. <hi>The Kings heart is in the band of the Lord, as the rivers of waters:</hi> As the huſband-man cuts out a chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel for the water-courſe with his ſpade, ſometimes lets it run in to water his fields, ſometimes ſets it off; So doth, the Lord more eaſily with the hearts, devices and counſells of Kings, he turneth them to water and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh his people, as the heart of <hi>Pharaoh</hi> to <hi>Joſeph,</hi> of <hi>Darius</hi> to <hi>Daniel,</hi> of <hi>Cyrus</hi> to the <hi>Jews:</hi> ſometimes he bears them off, when they would run impetuouſly to do hurt, as he did with divers of the Roman Emperours, and with <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth to the late Reformers, <hi>Melancthon, Pomeranius,</hi> and other famous men of God: whom, after he had conquered the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Princes, he diſmiſſed in ſafety, without laying any bands upon them at all.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe as God hath a ſpeciall work upon the hearts of Kings, ſo his work on them is of ſpeciall concernment to the Church. How the heart of a King is inclined, is of all earthly concernments, moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable: for, it is like the palme of the horologe, to tell the time, how Gods heart is inclined towards a people; when the Lord is angry with a people, he ſaith, he will make ſuch as hate him, reign over them; and when he is pacified, he giveth them Kings according to his own heart: So that the inclination of a Kings heart, is the ſign of Gods favour or diſpleaſure to a people. When God was to puniſh <hi>Judah,</hi> he ſet a <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſeh</hi> over them, who, though he was well educated under <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> yet proved he a fierce King. Again, when God was pacified, he ſets a <hi>Joſiah</hi> over them, who, though he was miſ-educated under <hi>Amon,</hi> yet had he a tender heart towards the people.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Becauſe Kings have, above all others, a difficult task and moſt weighty charge: great dominion carries with it alwayes a great care, which doth many times <hi>make ſleep depart from their eyes, Eſth.</hi> 6.1. The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid of himſelf, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.28. that beſide his troubles with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the care of all the Churches lay upon him: So Princes have the care
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:102408:10"/>of all their Subjects lying upon them, beſide the many dangers they are oftentimes incompaſſed with above others, The enemies of the publick peace being like the King of <hi>Syria,</hi> who commanded his Captains to fight neither againſt ſmall nor great, ſave againſt the King, 1 <hi>Kin.</hi> 22.31.</p>
            <p>You ſee then your duty: ſet about it. The King is more obliged to them who pray for him, and for his life and health, than to thoſe who drink his health in vain carrouſes, So he ſaith himſelf in his late Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation. Some that are here on this ſolemn day, I believe, have no great plenty, cannot command ſtrong drink, cannot come at a rich table, a cup running over: Let ſuch go home and pray this prayer aright, with ſtrong and fervent affection, <hi>God ſave the King.</hi> This will do him more good than all the healths that others can drink to him.</p>
            <p>And that you may know what particulars to minde in uſing theſe words, on this ſolemn day, I ſhall give you the deſcant of this ſhort word of prayer, in theſe few particulars, 1. In the Original Hebrew (as you have heard) it is, <hi>Let the King live.</hi> Then, 1. minde his natural life, to pray God that it may be precious in the Lords ſight, <hi>Ezr.</hi> 6.10. <hi>Darius</hi> renewed <hi>Cyrus</hi> Decree in favour of the <hi>Jews,</hi> with many additi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal benefits, That they might offer ſacrifices unto the God of heaven, and pray for the life of the King.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Minde his civil life, that he may live in Honour, Freedom and Safety: that is a main thing in the King's life, he is no living King without his Honour. Pray for that which God gave to <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 21.5. That Honour and Majeſty may be laid upon him. It is a great mercy from God to Kings, when he maintains their eſteem in the hearts of their people; much of God is ſeen in this.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Minde his ſpiritual life, that he may live a moſt Chriſtian King, a ſure partaker of the Faith whereof he is a defender. <hi>David</hi> begins the Pſalm of prayer for the King (to wit. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 72.) with this, <hi>Give the King thy judgments, O God, and thy righteouſneſs:</hi> all that is good, all grace is called by the name of <hi>righteouſneſs;</hi> and Gods Laws and Judgments, are the Rules of all Righteouſneſſe. And it is a moſt excellent word to remember at this time, (when the King hath to do with men of ſeveral judgments and wayes, and ſome will be ready to ſay, this is my counſel and judgment, and this is mine) Now, Lord, give <hi>Thy</hi> judgments to the King <hi>Thy</hi> counſels; hold forth theſe clearly to him.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Minde his eternal life: Good Kings have a two-fold eternall life,
<list>
                  <item>1. An eternal life in this world, in the long duration of their race and progeny. Let us minde this, to pray God that we may never want one of the Line to ſway the Scepter, as long as the world ſtandeth, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89.36, 37. That <hi>his ſeed may endure for ever, and his throne may be as the Sun before God, and be eſtabliſhed for ever as the Moon, and as a faithfull witneſs in heaven.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. There is a life eternal, properly ſo called: Remember this alſo, that our King may be an heir of eternal life
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:102408:11"/>in heaven after he hath lived many happy dayes here. All Chriſtian Kings, ſince the dayes of <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> have born a Croſs upon the top of their Crowns: there is no Poperie in it, But to teach them, that they muſt bear the croſs of Chriſt, as well as other Chriſtians: And if they do ſo, and exalt the croſs of Chriſt above their Crown, God will give them a Crown of glory above their croſs, according to Gods promiſe; <hi>James</hi> 1.12 <hi>Bleſſed is the man that endureth temptation: for when he is tryed, he ſhall receive the crown of life.</hi> Our King hath born the croſs before the Crown; and when he hath got the crown, there is no crown without a heavie croſs; But let our Prayer to God for him, be, That he may ſo bear the earthly Crown and the croſſes of it, that he may aſſuredly poſſeſſe the Crown of life.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Will you a little take the words as we have them tranſlated and as we uſe them. We ſay, <hi>God ſave the King;</hi> and there is a twofold <hi>Saving</hi> we ſhould minde, 1. One poſitively, when God bleſſeth, proſpereth, guideth, governeth and endueth a King with graces and gifts needfull for his place: this is the Lord's Salvation, wherein the Kings glory is great, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 21.5. Let it be our prayer to God then, as it is, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 80.17. <hi>Let thy hand be upon the man of thy right hand,</hi> that God may make him ſtrong for himſelf, giving to him wiſdom, courage and zeal to the honour and glory of God; juſtice, temperance and every other Royall endument.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Another <hi>Saving</hi> privativly, to wit, when God delivereth from all evills and dangers both bodily and ſpiritual. Minde this alſo: Pray God ſave the King from conſpiracies and treaſons, from all enemies and falſe friends. <hi>David</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, a King, hath a terrible prayer againſt the Kings enemies, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 21.9, 10. <hi>Make them as a fiery oven in the time of thine anger—That their fruit may be deſtroyea from the earth, and their ſeed from the children of men. Abigail,</hi> a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, ſhe hath a notable prayer againſt the enemies of <hi>David,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 25.29. <hi>Let the ſoul of my Lord, be bound up in the bundle of life with the Lord his God; and the ſouls of thine enemies, ſlung out as out of the midle of a ſling.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But pray that he may be delivered from ſpiritual evils and dangers, much more, God ſave the King from all wickedneſſe, <hi>Prov.</hi> 16.4. It is abomination to Kings to commit wickedneſſe, above all others; for, the Throne is eſtabliſhed by righteouſneſſe: and God ſave him from evill counſellers, <hi>Take away the wicked from the King, and his throne ſhall be eſtabliſhed;</hi> and from lyars and flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers that are a very Peſt in the Courts of Kings. <hi>Prov.</hi> 29.12. <hi>If a Ruler hearken to lies, all his ſervants are wicked.</hi> Pray God to ſave him from wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the precious Intereſts of Chriſts Kingdom, But that be may employ all the intereſts of his Kingdom in ſubordination to Chriſt, uſing for the Lord all the honour and authority he hath received from the Lord.</p>
            <p>And now, for concluſion of all, I ſhall ſay but this word; That ſame God who hath ſaved our King hithertils, even from the womb; who ſaved him when he was hid in the Oak; That gracious God who put his vail about him in his diſguiſe; That God who helped him, when his neareſt relations proved but unkind to him; He who provided for him in his wants, comforted him in his ſtraits, ſtrengthened him in his temptations, in <hi>France, Holland, Flanders, Germany</hi> and <hi>Spain;</hi> Even that gracious God, who hath ſeen and numbred all his Troubles, and delivered him, continue his Salvation with him for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:102408:11"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
